Banks McLaurin, Jr. stereograph collection
DeGolyer Library
- Stereoscopes, True-Vue and View-Master Viewers, and Magic Lantern Projectors, Series 17:
  - 7. "Ideal" viewer, patented 28 July 1903 by C.H. Graves. Includes a book with a set of 24 views, Round About – Jerusalem which fits over the slide rail of the Ideal viewer. Bought at Johnson Antique Show at Plano Centre on 29 May 1994, from Kilbridge Antiques of Sapulpa, OK for $140
  - 8. Keystone View Co. stereoscope with wood slide and frame, metal hood, undated. Bought at Brimfield, MA on May 12, 1995.
  - 9. The Corte-Scope, Cleveland, OH, metal viewer, patent pending. Bought at Little Red Hen Antiques, Paso Robles, CA on Oct. 8, 1992 along with a few Corte-Scope views and some German eye correction cards (30). $26 and $49 for cards.
  - 10. Keystone No. 50 Home Training Manual Stereoscope with Keystone No. 50 Home-Training Manual, Patent No.160196, Keystone View Co., Meadville, PA, Made in USA. Founded in 1892. Maroon plastic viewer purchased in box with instructions and boxed set of 12 stereos EC-41 through EC-52 on 5/6/93 at Collectors Antique Mall for $45. 1340 Delta, 12 stereo set in labeled box, each stereo labeled B0 3. (Box 23)
    - EC 41 Empire State Bldg.
    - EC 42 U.S. Capital Building and grounds from the air
    - EC 43 Boulder Dam
    - EC 44 Niagara Falls
    - EC 45 Birds
    - EC 46 Sensitive Plant
    - EC 47 Congo Fisherman
    - EC 48 Orchid Plant
    - EC 49 Dogs being trained
    - EC 50 Scene in Rockies
    - EC 51 Landscape
    - EC 52 Landscape
  - 11. "Imperial," D.R.G.M. No. 157580. "Fur diesen Apparat, sind, passende Bilder, von Landschaften und Genresachen, stets vorhanden, Weitere, Erganzung Derselben, in Vorbereitun." Sold in box with chocolates ca. 1890. Small viewer with one view bought in Copenhagen, Denmark on June 25, 1992.
  - 12. "The Pocket Rotoscope," the Rotary Photographic Co., LD. 12 New Union St., London Works: West Drayton. Small green, yellow and gold box with built-in viewer and stereos inside. Purchased 10/29/93 at New Market; MD at Comus Antiques; bought with 10 stereos to go with it for $100.
  - 13. Stereoindupong M.B.H., Frankfurt, D.R.O.M. "The American Express Company Luxury Cruise on the R.M.S. Mauritania to the Mediterranean, 66 days. Leaving New York February 7, 1923." Black folding metal viewer with stereos in maroon box.
  - 14. Stereograms Ltd. Pale blue and black plastic viewer and small color transparency stereographs in blue leather box.
  - 15. "Travelscope, 3rd Dimension, Natural Vision Photographs," manufactured by Keystone View Co. a set of views in a small dark blue box for the Century of Progress Exposition, Chicago, IL, 1934.
  - 16. Raumbild viewer, manufactured ca. 1939 with 10 2.25 x 5" views manufactured by Otto Schonstein, Munchen, Germany. Bought at Heritage Antiques in West, TX on Nov. 6, 1993 for $100. (Box 24)
  - 17. Stereo Book. U.S. Occupied Zone of Germany. Box in the shape of a book with black metal viewer inside and 36 stereos. Stereos are 2.35" x 5." Made in Germany in the occupied zone in 1945 by Raumbild-Werkstatte, Munchen. Viewer bought in July 1996 in Chatham, MA.
  - 18. Deutschland im Raumbild viewer and 2 ¼ x 5" stereos in red leather box, ca. 1948-1952. Includes five series: Bavaria; Berlin-Potsdam; German views, series I, series II; Historic Buildings; XV Olympics, Helsinki, 1952.
  - 19. Nu-Scope, "It can be put away when not in use," the Nu-Scope Co., Reading, PA, patent applied for. Stereoscope and box with photograph of two girls on lid with stereoscope with pink hood inside. Bought on May 27, 1994 at The Antique Marketplace on Burnet Road, Austin, TX for $95 including tax and 16 stereos (lithographs).
  - 20. Taylor-Merchant Stereopticon 707. Three black fold-up cardboard viewers. Bought with sets of stereo reproductions – 72 in all.
  - 21. 3 D Book Viewer in envelope, made by Stiles Studio.
  - 22. Tru-Vue, Inc., Rock Island, IL, viewer with 12 rolls including "A Century of Progress" and Christmas themes in special inlaid Christmas box with catalogue, See the World! True-Vue Positively Life-like. and list of films available. Bought at Unlimited, Ltd. on 9/10/94 for $92.01. (Box 25)
  - 23. Stereoscope RoMo Standard, brown plastic viewer. Made in France. Bought with 5-21 picture slides at Collections Antique store in Buenos Aires, Argentina on Feb. 21, 1995. The slides were patented. (Old version of viewer #24.)
  - 24. Stereoscope Lestrade Simplex, red plastic viewer. Bought with 3-8 picture slides at the Hospices de Beaune in Oct. 1994, Beaune, France. (See viewer #23.)
  - 25. View-Master, c. 1943 Model; Sawyers, Portland, OR. Purchased 10/29/93 at Limited – Unlimited, Dallas for $53 which included 6 reels.
  - 26. View-Master, patent 2,189, 265, Canadian patent 408893, British patent 538492, purchased at Unlimited, Ltd. on 5 May 1994 for $47 with 10 reels.
  - 27. Sawyer’s View-Master viewer in a brown and beige plastic box holding 100 view cards with Canadian, USA and British patents listed. Bought in Chatham, MA, July 1996.
  - 28. Sawyer View-Master, U.S. Patent 2189285, Portland, OR. Can. Pat 408893; Brit Pat. 538492. Bought at St. Luke’s Plaid Door April 1995 for $2.00.
  - 29. View-Master 3410 with 16 reels. Mfg. by Sawyer’s, Portland, OR in 1949. Bought from the Unlimited, Ltd. The Antique Mall, Dallas on Nov. 14, 1992 for $45.
  - 30. "Sawyer’s View-Master Junior Projector." Bought in the Sandwich, MA, doll museum in July 1996 for $35.
  - 31. View-Master, Model E; made by View Master, Portland, OR. Bought at the Antique Sampler Auction House, Inc., Arlington, TX on 29 March 1994 for $64.
  - 32. "Sawyer’s View-Master, Lighted Stereo Viewer." Brown plastic viewer bought in Austin, TX Sept. 21, 1996 for $35.
  - 33. View-Master, 1993 model; made by View-Master, Portland, OR. A subsidiary of Tyco Toys Ltd. Bought at Carlsbad Caverns Natl. Park, NM on Nov. 26, 1993 for $14.00.
  - 34. View-Master, 1994 model; made by Tyco; bought at Toys R’US, 15 Sept. 1994.
  - Romo Lestrade Cards and View-Master Reels (Box 26)
  - 1. Magic Lantern projector small in size, used kerosene lamp, but now use flashlight to be safe. Purchased in Georgetown, VA in 1976. (Box 27)
  - 2. Magic Lantern projector, Euphaneron, sold by E.G. Wood, 2, Queen St., Cheapside, London, England. Trade Mark MM. Uses light bulb. Bought Jan. 21, 1992 from Inwood Village Antiques for $179.
- Magic Lantern Slides, Series 18:
  - Magic Lantern Slide Series (Box 28)
    - 1. French glass lantern slides; humorous (narrow wooden box)
    - 2. American History, round with wooden frames
    - 3. Southern States, Set A (black case)
    - 4. Animals of North America C (wooden box)
    - 5. Mixed series of Russian, Animals, Religion, French Humor (wooden box)
    - 6. Mixed series of Japan, U.S., and Europe (black plastic box)
- McLaurin Notebooks, Series 19:
  Mr. McLaurin compiled five notebooks of personal information relating to his collecting, the photographers, companies, subjects, locations and stereoscopes represented in his collection. Some of these notes and lists have been incorporated into the finding aid using his subject headings with minor editing for consistency in format and terminology. His notes on purchasing the viewers are listed with the description.
  - Notebook I: Inventory of Stereo Photographers by State and Country; Alphabetical Listing of Photographers
    - 1. List of U.S. and Foreign Photographers by Location
    - 2. List of U.S. and Foreign Stereo Photographers and Distributors
    - 3. Inventory of Total Number of Stereographs, Lithos, Magic Lantern Slides and Viewers
  - Notebook II: Stereo Numbers and Stereo Publishers
    - 1. List of Stereos by Number with Description
  - Notebook III: Keystone, Underwood Underwood, and Boxed Sets
    - 1. List of Keystone View Co. U.S. and Foreign Stereographs
    - 2. List of Underwood Underwood U.S. and Foreign Stereographs
    - 3. List of Keystone View Co. U.S. and Foreign Boxed Sets
    - 4. List of Underwood Underwood U.S. and Foreign Boxed Sets
  - Notebook IV: Special Types: Lithos, Tissues, Viewers, and View-Master
    - 1. List of Tissues by Number
    - 2. Index of Lithographs by Number
    - 3. List of Viewers
    - 4. Miscellaneous Index by Number
    - 5. List of Magic Lantern, Viewers and Slides
    - 6. List of View-Master Viewers and Reels
  - Notebook V: Stereograph Listing and Photographers; Articles on Stereographs and Viewer History
    - 1. List of Stereo Viewers and Slides
    - 2. List of Photographers and List by Country and State
    - 3. Photocopy of chapter in Thomas J. Schlereth, Victorian America: Transformations in Everyday Life, 1876-1915 (New York, N.Y.: HarperCollins, 1991)
    - 4. Dates of World Fairs and Expositions
    - 5. Collection of assorted articles and photographs on stereo viewers and their history.